I grew up watching Star Trek. I love Star Trek.
لقد نشأت وأنا أشاهد ستار تريك. أنا أحب ستار تريك
Star Trek made me want to see alien creatures,
جعلني ستار تريك أريد مشاهدة المخلوقات الفضائية
creatures from a far-distant world.
مخلوقات من عالم بعيد
But basically, I figured out that I could find
ولكني اكتشفت أنني أستطيع إيجاد
those alien creatures right on Earth.
هذه المخلوقات الفضائية على الأرض.
And what I do is I study insects.
ما أقوم به هو دراسة الحشرات.
I'm obsessed with insects, particularly insect flight.
أنا مهووس بالحشرات وخاصةً طريقة طيرانها.
I think the evolution of insect flight is perhaps
وأعتقد أن تطور طيران الحشرات ربما يكون
one of the most important events in the history of life.
أحد أهم الأحداث في تاريخ الحياة.
Without insects, there'd be no flowering plants.
فمن دون الحشرات، لن تزهر النباتات.
Without flowering plants, there would be no
ومن دون ازدهار النباتات، لن تكون هناك
clever, fruit-eating primates giving TED Talks.
رئيسات ذكية آكلة للفواكة تقدّم محادثات TED.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now,
والآن،
David and Hidehiko and Ketaki
دايفيد وهيدهيكو وكيتاكي
gave a very compelling story about
أخبروا قصة مؤثرة جداً عن
the similarities between fruit flies and humans,
أوجه التشابة بين ذباب الفواكه والإنسان،
and there are many similarities,
وهناك العديد من أوجه التشابه
and so you might think that if humans are similar to fruit flies,
وقد تفكّر أنهّ إذا كان الإنسان يشبه الذباب،
the favorite behavior of a fruit fly might be this, for example --
قد يكون التصرف المفضل لذباب الحشرات مثل هذا على سبيل المثال
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
but in my talk, I don't want to emphasize on the similarities
ولكن في محادثتي، لا أريد التركيز على أوجه التشابه
between humans and fruit flies, but rather the differences,
بين الإنسان والذباب بل على أوجه الاختلاف،
and focus on the behaviors that I think fruit flies excel at doing.
والتركيز على التصرفات التي أعتقد أن ذباب الفواكة يتقن فعلها.
And so I want to show you a high-speed video sequence
ولذلك أريد أن أريكم فيديو عالي السرعة
of a fly shot at 7,000 frames per second in infrared lighting,
لذبابة صوّرت بسرعة 7000 لقطة في الثانية في ضوء بالأشعة تحت الحمراء،
and to the right, off-screen, is an electronic looming predator
وفي الشاشة اليمنى يوجد مفترس الكتروني
that is going to go at the fly.
والذي سيهاجم الذبابة.
The fly is going to sense this predator.
وستستشعر الذبابة هذا المفترس
It is going to extend its legs out.
وستمد ساقيها
It's going to sashay away
وستنطلق بعيداً
to live to fly another day.
لتعيش يوماً آخر.
Now I have carefully cropped this sequence
وقد قطعت هذه السلسلة بعناية
to be exactly the duration of a human eye blink,
لكي تزامن رمشة عين الإنسان بالضبط
so in the time that it would take you to blink your eye,
في الوقت الذي سترمش فيه
the fly has seen this looming predator,
ستكون الذبابة قد رأت المفترس
estimated its position, initiated a motor pattern to fly it away,
وتوقعت مكانه واستخدمت نمط طيران للفرار منه
beating its wings at 220 times a second as it does so.
ضاربة أجنحتها 220 مرة في الثانية كما وُضِح في الصورة.
I think this is a fascinating behavior
وأعتقد أن هذا التصرف رائع
that shows how fast the fly's brain can process information.
والذي يوضح مدى سرعة دماغ الذبابة في معالجة المعلومات
Now, flight -- what does it take to fly?
والآن، الطيران-- ماذا يتطلب الطيران؟
Well, in order to fly, just as in a human aircraft,
لكي تطير الذبابة، كما هو الحال في طائرة صنعها الإنسان
you need wings that can generate sufficient aerodynamic forces,
تحتاج إلى أجنحة قادرة على توليد قوى هوائية كافية
you need an engine sufficient to generate the power required for flight,
تحتاج إلى محرك قادر على توليد القوة المطلوبة للطيران
and you need a controller,
وتحتاج إلى جهاز تحكم،
and in the first human aircraft, the controller was basically
وفي أول طائرة صنعها الإنسان، كان جهاز التحكم
the brain of Orville and Wilbur sitting in the cockpit.
هو دماغي أورفيل وويلبر الجالسين في غرفة القيادة.
Now, how does this compare to a fly?
والآن، كيف نقارن ذلك بالذبابة؟
Well, I spent a lot of my early career trying to figure out
حسناً، قضيت معظم وقتي في بداية حياتي المهنية في محاولة معرفة
how insect wings generate enough force to keep the flies in the air.
كيف تقوم أجنحة الحشرات بتوليد قوة كافية لإبقاء الذباب في الهواء.
And you might have heard how engineers proved
وربما قد سمعت كيف أثبت المهندسون
that bumblebees couldn't fly.
أن النحل الطنان لا يستطيع الطيران.
Well, the problem was in thinking that the insect wings
حسناً، كانت المشكلة في التفكير أن أجنحة الحشرات
function in the way that aircraft wings work. But they don't.
تعمل بنفس طريقة أجنحة الطائرات و هذا ليس صحيحاً
And we tackle this problem by building giant,
وعالجنا هذه المشكلة عن طريق بناء
dynamically scaled model robot insects
نموذج حشرة آلي عملاق مصمم بشكل ديناميكي
that would flap in giant pools of mineral oil
يمكنه أن يرفرف في أحواض ضخمة من الزيت المعدني
where we could study the aerodynamic forces.
حيث نستطيع دراسة القوى الهوائية.
And it turns out that the insects flap their wings
واتضح أن الحشرات ترفرف أجنحنها
in a very clever way, at a very high angle of attack
بطريقة ذكية جداً وبزاوية عالية جداً للهجوم
that creates a structure at the leading edge of the wing,
والذي يخلق هيكلا للحافة الأمامية للجناح،
a little tornado-like structure called a leading edge vortex,
وهناك هيكل صغير يشبه الإعصار يسمـى دوامة الحافة الأمامية،
and it's that vortex that actually enables the wings
وهذه الدوامة تتيح للأجنحة
to make enough force for the animal to stay in the air.
إنشاء قوة كافية ليبقى الحيوان في الجو.
But the thing that's actually most -- so, what's fascinating
والأمر في الواقع الأكثر -- الرائع حول هذا الأمر
is not so much that the wing has some interesting morphology.
هو ليس أن الجناح لديه علم تشكل (مورفولوجيا) مثير للاهنتمام فحسب.
What's clever is the way the fly flaps it,
بل الشيء الذكي هو طريقة رفرفة الآجنحة
which of course ultimately is controlled by the nervous system,
و الذي بالطبع يتحكم به الجهاز العصبي،
and this is what enables flies to perform
وهذا يتيح للذباب لأداء
these remarkable aerial maneuvers.
حركات جوية رائعة.
Now, what about the engine?
والآن، ماذا بشأن المحرك؟
The engine of the fly is absolutely fascinating.
محرك الذباب رائع جداً.
They have two types of flight muscle:
لديها نوعان من عضلات الطيران:
so-called power muscle, which is stretch-activated,
ما يسمى بعضلات القوة، والتي تنشط بالامتداد،
which means that it activates itself and does not need to be controlled
وهذا يعني أنها تنشط نفسها ولا تحتاج إلى التحكم
on a contraction-by-contraction basis by the nervous system.
بواسطة قواعد الانكماش من قبل الجهاز العصبي.
It's specialized to generate the enormous power required for flight,
فهو مخصص لتوليد طاقة هائلة لازمة للطيران،
and it fills the middle portion of the fly,
وملء الجزء الأوسط من الذبابة
so when a fly hits your windshield,
لذا عندما تضرب الذبابة في الزجاج لأمامي لسيارتك
it's basically the power muscle that you're looking at.
فالذي رأيته هو في الأساس عضلة القوة.
But attached to the base of the wing
ولكن يتصل بقاعدة الجناح
is a set of little, tiny control muscles
عضلات تحكم صفيرة جداً
that are not very powerful at all, but they're very fast,
ليست قوية أبداً ولكنها سريعة جداً،
and they're able to reconfigure the hinge of the wing
وقادرة على إعادة تكوين مفصل الجناح
on a stroke-by-stroke basis,
بواسطة قواعد الضربات
and this is what enables the fly to change its wing
وهذا ما يتيح الذبابة لتغيير جناحها
and generate the changes in aerodynamic forces
وتوليد التغييرات في القوى الهوائية
which change its flight trajectory.
مما يؤدي إلى تغيير مسار طيرانها.
And of course, the role of the nervous system is to control all this.
وبالطبع دور الجهاز العصبي التحكم بكل هذا.
So let's look at the controller.
لننظر إلى جهاز التحكم.
Now flies excel in the sorts of sensors
يتميز الذباب بأجهزة الاستشعار
that they carry to this problem.
والتي يحملونها لهذه المشكلة.
They have antennae that sense odors and detect wind detection.
لديهم قرون استشعار والتي تستشعر الروائح وتكشف التيارات الهوائية.
They have a sophisticated eye which is
عينها متطورة وتعتبر
the fastest visual system on the planet.
أسرع جهاز بصري في العالم.
They have another set of eyes on the top of their head.
ولديها عيون أخرى في أعلى رأسها.
We have no idea what they do.
لا نعلم ما وظيفتها.
They have sensors on their wing.
ولديها أجهزة استشعار على أجنحتها.
Their wing is covered with sensors, including sensors
وأجنحتها مغطاة بأجهزة استشعار، بما في ذلك أجهزة استشعار
that sense deformation of the wing.
والتي تستشعر تشوه الجناح.
They can even taste with their wings.
وبإمكانها أيضاً التذوق بواسطة جناحها.
One of the most sophisticated sensors a fly has
وأحد أجهزة استشعار الذباب المتطورة للغاية
is a structure called the halteres.
هو هيكل يسمى "الهالتيرس".
The halteres are actually gyroscopes.
وهي عبارة عن أجهزة توجيه.
These devices beat back and forth about 200 hertz during flight,
هذه الأجهزة تنبض أثناء الطيران ذهاباً و إياباً بمعدل 200 هرتز
and the animal can use them to sense its body rotation
ويمكن أن تستخدمها الحيوانات لاستشعار دوران جسمها
and initiate very, very fast corrective maneuvers.
واتخاذ حركات تصحيحة سريعة جداً.
But all of this sensory information has to be processed
ولكن جميع هذه المعلومات الاستشعارية يجب أن تعالج
by a brain, and yes, indeed, flies have a brain,
بواسطة الدماغ، ونعم في الواقع، الذباب لديه دماغ
a brain of about 100,000 neurons.
دماغ يحتوي على 100,000 خلاية عصبية
Now several people at this conference
وحالياً، العديد من الناس في هذا المؤتمر
have already suggested that fruit flies could serve neuroscience
اقترحوا مسبقاً أن ذباب الفواكة قد تخدم علم الأعصاب
because they're a simple model of brain function.
لأنهم يمثلون نموذجا مبسطا من وظائف الدماغ
And the basic punchline of my talk is,
والغرض من محادثتي هو
I'd like to turn that over on its head.
أود قلب هذا رأساً على عقب.
I don't think they're a simple model of anything.
لا أظن أنها نموذج مبسط لأي شيء.
And I think that flies are a great model.
بل أظن أن الذباب نموذج رائع.
They're a great model for flies.
نموذج رائع للذباب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And let's explore this notion of simplicity.
و لنستكشف نموذج البساطة هذا.
So I think, unfortunately, a lot of neuroscientists,
أعتقد، للأسف، أن العديد من علماء الأعصاب
we're all somewhat narcissistic.
نرجسيون قليلاً.
When we think of brain, we of course imagine our own brain.
عندما نفكر في الدماغ، نتخيل بالطبع دماغنا.
But remember that this kind of brain,
ولكن تذكر أن هذا النوع من الدماغ
which is much, much smaller
أصغر بكثير
— instead of 100 billion neurons, it has 100,000 neurons —
فبدلاً من وجود 100 مليار خلية عصبية لديها فقط 100,000 خلية عصبية
but this is the most common form of brain on the planet
ولكنه من أكثر أشكال الدماغ شيوعاً في الأرض
and has been for 400 million years.
ولازال كذلك منذ 400 مليون سنة.
And is it fair to say that it's simple?
وهل من العدل أن نقول أنه بسيط؟
Well, it's simple in the sense that it has fewer neurons,
حسناً، بساطته تكمن في أنه يحتوي على خلايا عصبية أقل
but is that a fair metric?
لكن هل هذا قياس عادل؟
And I would propose it's not a fair metric.
أود أن أقترح أن هذا ليس قياسا عادلا.
So let's sort of think about this. I think we have to compare --
لنفكر قليلاً حول هذا. أعتقد أننا نجب أن نقارن بين --
(Laughter) —
(ضحك)
we have to compare the size of the brain
يحب أن نقارن بين حجم الدماغ
with what the brain can do.
مع قدراته
So I propose we have a Trump number,
لذا أقترح أن يكون لدينا عدد ترامب
and the Trump number is the ratio of this man's
وعدد ترامب يمثل نسبة
behavioral repertoire to the number of neurons in his brain.
سلوك هذا الرجل مقارنة بعدد الخلايا العصبية في دماغه
We'll calculate the Trump number for the fruit fly.
سنقوم بحساب عدد ترامب للذباب
Now, how many people here think the Trump number
وحالياً، كم شخص حاضر يعتقد أن عدد ترامب
is higher for the fruit fly?
أعلى لدى الذبابة؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It's a very smart, smart audience.
الجمهور ذكي جداً.
Yes, the inequality goes in this direction, or I would posit it.
نعم، هناك عدم مساواة في هذا الاتجاه.
Now I realize that it is a little bit absurd
وأنا أدرك الآن أنه سخيف قليلاً
to compare the behavioral repertoire of a human to a fly.
مقارنة سلوك إنسان بسلوك ذبابة.
But let's take another animal just as an example. Here's a mouse.
ولنأخذ حيواناً آخر كمثال. هذه فأرة
A mouse has about 1,000 times as many neurons as a fly.
الخلايا العصبية للفأرة أكثر بـ 1,000 مرة من الذبابة
I used to study mice. When I studied mice,
كنت أدرس الفئران من قبل. وعندما كنت أدرسها
I used to talk really slowly.
كنت أتكلم ببطء شديد.
And then something happened when I started to work on flies.
وحدث شيء ما عندما بدأت بالعمل على الذباب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I think if you compare the natural history of flies and mice,
وأعتقد إذا قارنت التاريخ الطبيعي للفئران و الذباب،
it's really comparable. They have to forage for food.
فستجد أنه يتشابة. كلاهما يسعون للبحث عن الطعام.
They have to engage in courtship.
وينخرطون في المغازلة.
They have sex. They hide from predators.
ويمارسون الجنس. ويختبؤن من الحيوانات المفترسة
They do a lot of the similar things.
يقومون بالكثير من الأمور المماثلة
But I would argue that flies do more.
ولكني أزعم بأن الذباب يفعل أكثر من ذلك
So for example, I'm going to show you a sequence,
فعلى سبيل المثال، سأعرض لكم سلسلة
and I have to say, some of my funding comes from the military,
وأود أن أقول بأن بعض من تمويلي يأتي من الجيش
so I'm showing this classified sequence
لذا سأعرض لكم هذه السلسلة المصنفة
and you cannot discuss it outside of this room. Okay?
ولا يمكنم مناقشتها خارج هذه الغرفة، حسناً؟
So I want you to look at the payload
أريدكم أن تنظروا إلى الحمولة
at the tail of the fruit fly.
في ذنب ذبابة الفاكهة.
Watch it very closely,
راقبوها عن كثب.
and you'll see why my six-year-old son
وسترون لماذا ابني ذو الست سنوات
now wants to be a neuroscientist.
يريد أن يصبح عالم أعصاب.
Wait for it.
انتظروا.
Pshhew.
بشيو.
So at least you'll admit that if fruit flies are not as clever as mice,
على الأقل ستعترفون بأنه إذا كان الذباب ليس ذكياً كالفئران
they're at least as clever as pigeons. (Laughter)
فهم على الأقل ذكيون كالحمام. (ضحك)
Now, I want to get across that it's not just a matter of numbers
والآن أريد أن أوضح لكم بأن الأمر ليس متعلقا بالأرقام فقط
but also the challenge for a fly to compute
بل هو أيضاً تحدي للذبابة لحساب
everything its brain has to compute with such tiny neurons.
كل شيء، يقوم دماغها بالحساب باستخدام خلايا عصبية صغيرة
So this is a beautiful image of a visual interneuron from a mouse
هذه صورة جميلة لعصبون بصري متوسط لفأرة
that came from Jeff Lichtman's lab,
أحضرت من مختبر جيف ليشتمان
and you can see the wonderful images of brains
ويمكنكم أن تروا صورة جميلة للدماغ
that he showed in his talk.
والتي عرضها في محادثته.
But up in the corner, in the right corner, you'll see,
وفي الزاوية اليمنى سترون
at the same scale, a visual interneuron from a fly.
بنفس النطاق، سترون عصبونا بصريا متوسطا لذبابة
And I'll expand this up.
سأكبر هذه الصورة
And it's a beautifully complex neuron.
هذه خلايا عصبية معقدة بشكل جميل.
It's just very, very tiny, and there's lots of biophysical challenges
ولكنها صغيرة جداً وتحتوي على الكثير من التحديات الفيزيائية الحيوية
with trying to compute information with tiny, tiny neurons.
تحاول أن تحسب المعلومات بخلايا عصبية صغيرة جداً.
How small can neurons get? Well, look at this interesting insect.
ما مدى صغر الخلايا العصبية؟ حسناً، انظروا إلى هذه الحشرة المثيرة للاهتمام.
It looks sort of like a fly. It has wings, it has eyes,
تشبة الذبابة. لديها أجنحة و عينان
it has antennae, its legs, complicated life history,
و لديها قرون استشعار وساقان وتاريخ حياة معقد
it's a parasite, it has to fly around and find caterpillars
إنها طفيلية. يجب أن تطير و تبحث عن اليرقات
to parasatize,
لتقتات عليها.
but not only is its brain the size of a salt grain,
ولكن ليس فقط لأن حجم دماغها يساوي حجم حبة الملح
which is comparable for a fruit fly,
الأمر الذي يشابه ذبابة الفاكهة،
it is the size of a salt grain.
هو بحجم حبة ملح.
So here's some other organisms at the similar scale.
وهنا بعض الكائنات الحية الأخرى بنفس الحجم.
This animal is the size of a paramecium and an amoeba,
حجم هذا الحيوان مثل حجم البراميسيوم والأمبيا
and it has a brain of 7,000 neurons that's so small --
ودماغه يحتوي على 7,000 خلية عصبية وهذا صغير جداً --
you know these things called cell bodies you've been hearing about,
وتسمى هذا الأشياء خلايا الجسم والتي قد سمعتم عنها
where the nucleus of the neuron is?
أين نواة الخلية العصبية؟
This animal gets rid of them because they take up too much space.
يتخلص منها هذا الحيوان لأنها تشغل مساحة كبيرة.
So this is a session on frontiers in neuroscience.
هذه دورة عن حدود علم الأعصاب
I would posit that one frontier in neuroscience is to figure out how the brain of that thing works.
وأود أن أقول أن أحد حدود عمل الأعصاب هو اكتشاف كيف يعمل دماغ هذا الشيء
But let's think about this. How can you make a small number of neurons do a lot?
لكن دعونا نفكر حول هذا. كيف يمكنك جعل عدد صغير من الخلايا العصبية تقوم بالكثير؟
And I think, from an engineering perspective,
وأعتقد، من وجهة نظر هندسية،
you think of multiplexing.
قد تفكر في التضاعف.
You can take a hardware and have that hardware
يمكنك أن تأخذ جهاز وتجعل هذا الجهاز
do different things at different times,
يقوم بأشياء مختلفة في أوقات مختلفة
or have different parts of the hardware doing different things.
أو تجعل أجزاء مختلفة من الجهاز تقوم بأشياء مختلفة
And these are the two concepts I'd like to explore.
وهذين المفهومين أريد أن استكشفهما.
And they're not concepts that I've come up with,
وهي ليست مفاهيم قمت باقتراحها
but concepts that have been proposed by others in the past.
ولكنها مفاهيم اقترحها آخرون من قبل.
And one idea comes from lessons from chewing crabs.
وأتت إحدى الأفكار من دروس مضغ السراطين
And I don't mean chewing the crabs.
ولا أقصد مضغك للسراطين.
I grew up in Baltimore, and I chew crabs very, very well.
ترعرت في بالتيمور، وأمضغ السراطين بشكل جيد جداً.
But I'm talking about the crabs actually doing the chewing.
ولكنني أقصد السراطين هي التي تقوم فعلاً بالمضغ.
Crab chewing is actually really fascinating.
مضغ السراطين شيء رائع جداً.
Crabs have this complicated structure under their carapace
لدى السراطين بنية معقدة تحت درعها
called the gastric mill
تسمى بالطاحونة المعوية
that grinds their food in a variety of different ways.
والتي تطحن الطعام بطرق مختلفة.
And here's an endoscopic movie of this structure.
وهذا فلم بالمنظار الداخلي لهذه البنية
The amazing thing about this is that it's controlled
والرائع حول هذا الأمر هو أنه يتحكم به
by a really tiny set of neurons, about two dozen neurons
خلايا عصبية صغيرة جداً يبلغ عددها حوالي 24 خلية عصبية
that can produce a vast variety of different motor patterns,
والتي تنتج مجموعة متنوعة من أنماط الحركة
and the reason it can do this is that this little tiny ganglion
وتستطيع القيام بذلك بسبب أن هذه الكتلة العصبية الصغيرة
in the crab is actually inundated by many, many neuromodulators.
في السرطان مملوءة بمعدلات عصبية.
You heard about neuromodulators earlier.
وقد سمعتم بالمعدلات العصبية مسبقاً.
There are more neuromodulators
ويوجد المزيد من المعدلات العصبية
that alter, that innervate this structure than actually neurons in the structure,
التي تغير وتزود هذه البنية بالأعصاب أكثر مما تقوم به الخلايا العصبية الموجودة في البنية
and they're able to generate a complicated set of patterns.
وهي قادرة على إنشاء مجموعة معقدة من الأنماط.
And this is the work by Eve Marder and her many colleagues
وهذا عمل إيف ماردر و العديد من زملائها
who've been studying this fascinating system
الذين قاموا بدراسة هذا النظام الرائع
that show how a smaller cluster of neurons
الذي يوضح كيف يمكن لأصغر عنقود من الخلايا العصبية
can do many, many, many things
القيام بالعديد من الأمور
because of neuromodulation that can take place on a moment-by-moment basis.
بسبب عمليات التعديل العصبية التي تحدث في أي لحظة.
So this is basically multiplexing in time.
وهذه ستتضاعف مع الوقت
Imagine a network of neurons with one neuromodulator.
تخيل شبكة خلايا عصبية بمعدل عصبي واحد.
You select one set of cells to perform one sort of behavior,
تختار مجموعة واحدة من الخلايا لأداء نوع واحد من السلوك
another neuromodulator, another set of cells,
ومعدل عصببي آخر، ومجموعة خلايا أخرى
a different pattern, and you can imagine
ونمط مختلف، و يمكنك أن تتخيل
you could extrapolate to a very, very complicated system.
أنك تعمل على نظام معقد للغاية.
Is there any evidence that flies do this?
هل هناك أي دليل على أن الذباب يقوم بفعل هذا؟
Well, for many years in my laboratory and other laboratories around the world,
حسناً، كنا لسنوات عدة في مختبري و المختبرات الأخرى في العالم
we've been studying fly behaviors in little flight simulators.
ندرس سلوكيات الذباب في أجهزة محاكاة الطيران الصغيرة.
You can tether a fly to a little stick.
يمكنك ربط الذبابة على عصا صغيرة.
You can measure the aerodynamic forces it's creating.
و يمكنك قياس القوى الهوائية التي تنشأها.
You can let the fly play a little video game
ويمكنك ترك الذبابة لتلعب لعبة فيديو صغيرة
by letting it fly around in a visual display.
عن طريق تركها لتطير في جهاز عرض مرئي
So let me show you a little tiny sequence of this.
دعوني أعرض لكم سلسلة صغيرة من هذا.
Here's a fly
هذه ذبابة
and a large infrared view of the fly in the flight simulator,
وعرض كبير بالأشعة تحت الحمراء للذبابة في جهاز محاكاة الطيران،
and this is a game the flies love to play.
وهذه لعبة يحب الذباب أن يلعبها.
You allow them to steer towards the little stripe,
تدعهم ليطيروا باتجاه الخطوط الصغيرة
and they'll just steer towards that stripe forever.
وسيطيروا باتجاهها للأبد
It's part of their visual guidance system.
هذا جزء من نظام التوجيه البصري لديهم.
But very, very recently, it's been possible
ولكن في الآونة الأخيرة، كان من الممكن
to modify these sorts of behavioral arenas for physiologies.
تعديل هذه الأشكال من المجالات السلوكية لعلم وظائف الأعضاء
So this is the preparation that one of my former post-docs,
هذا إعداد لباحث سابق لدي، في مرحلة ما بعد الدكتوراه
Gaby Maimon, who's now at Rockefeller, developed,
جابي ميامون، والذي يعمل حالياً في روكيفيلير، قام بتطوير
and it's basically a flight simulator
جهاز محاكاة الطيران
but under conditions where you actually can stick an electrode
ولكن في الحالات التي تستطيع فيها إلصاق قطب كهربائي
in the brain of the fly and record
في دماغ الذبابة وتسجيل
from a genetically identified neuron in the fly's brain.
الخلية العصبية المعدلة وراثياً في دماغ الذبابة.
And this is what one of these experiments looks like.
وهذا ما تبدو عليه إحدى التجارب.
It was a sequence taken from another post-doc in the lab,
كانت سلسلة مأخوذة من باحثة أخرى في المختبر في مرحلة ما بعد الدكتوراه
Bettina Schnell.
بيتينا شنيل.
The green trace at the bottom is the membrane potential
البقايا الخضراء في الأسفل هي الغشاء المحتمل
of a neuron in the fly's brain,
للخلية العصبية في دماغ الذبابة
and you'll see the fly start to fly, and the fly is actually
وسترى أن الذبابة تبدأ بالطيران والذبابة في الواقع
controlling the rotation of that visual pattern itself
تتحكم بدوران النمط البصري نفسه
by its own wing motion,
عن طريق حركة جناحها
and you can see this visual interneuron
وتستطيع أن ترى العصبون البصري
respond to the pattern of wing motion as the fly flies.
يستجيب لنمط الجناح أثناء طيران الذبابة.
So for the first time we've actually been able to record
ولأول مرة استطعنا أن نسجل
from neurons in the fly's brain while the fly
الخلايا العصبية في دماغ الذبابة أثناء
is performing sophisticated behaviors such as flight.
أداء الذبابة لتصرفات متطورة كالطيران
And one of the lessons we've been learning
وأحد الدروس التي نتعلمها
is that the physiology of cells that we've been studying
هي فيزيولوجيا الخلايا التي كنا ندرسها
for many years in quiescent flies
لسنوات عدة في الذباب الهادئ
is not the same as the physiology of those cells
وهي لا تماثل فزيولوجيا الخلايا
when the flies actually engage in active behaviors
عنما ينخرط الذباب في تصرفات نشطة
like flying and walking and so forth.
مثل الطيران و المشي وغيرها.
And why is the physiology different?
ولماذا تختلف الفزيولوجيا؟
Well it turns out it's these neuromodulators,
يتيبين أن هذه المعدلات العصبية
just like the neuromodulators in that little tiny ganglion in the crabs.
تشبه المعدلات العصبية في الكتلة العصبية الموجودة في السراطين
So here's a picture of the octopamine system.
وهذه صورة لجهاز الأكتوبامين.
Octopamine is a neuromodulator
الأكتوبامين هو معدل عصبي
that seems to play an important role in flight and other behaviors.
والذي ببدو أنه يلعب دوراً مهماً في الطيران والتصرفات الأخرى.
But this is just one of many neuromodulators
ولكنه مجرد واحد من المعدلات العصبية
that's in the fly's brain.
الموجودة في دماغ الذبابة.
So I really think that, as we learn more,
ولهذا أعتقد حقاً، بقدر تعلمنا أكثر،
it's going to turn out that the whole fly brain
سيبدو أن دماغ الذبابة بأكمله
is just like a large version of this stomatogastric ganglion,
يشابه نسخة كبيرة للكتلة العصبية المعدية الفمية
and that's one of the reasons why it can do so much with so few neurons.
وهذا أحد أسباب قدرته على فعل الكثير بعدد قليل من الخلايا العصبية.
Now, another idea, another way of multiplexing
والآن، فكرة أخرى، طريقة أخرى للمضاعفة
is multiplexing in space,
هي المضاعفة في الحيز
having different parts of a neuron
أي جعل أجزاء مختلفة في الخلية العصبية
do different things at the same time.
تقوم بأشياء مخنلفة في نفس الوقت.
So here's two sort of canonical neurons
وهنا نوعان من الخلايا العصبية تقليدية
from a vertebrate and an invertebrate,
من حيوانات فقرية و لافقرية،
a human pyramidal neuron from Ramon y Cajal,
ومن خلايا عصبية هرمية من رامون كاهال،
and another cell to the right, a non-spiking interneuron,
وفي اليمين خلية أخرى، عصبون غير شوكي
and this is the work of Alan Watson and Malcolm Burrows many years ago,
وهذا عمل ألان واتسون ومالكوم بوروس منذ سنوات عدة،
and Malcolm Burrows came up with a pretty interesting idea
وقد اقترح مالكوم بوروس فكرة مثيرة للاهتمام
based on the fact that this neuron from a locust
بناءً على حقيقة أن الخلية العصبية للجراد
does not fire action potentials.
لا تطلق جهد الفعل.
It's a non-spiking cell.
فهي خلية شوكية
So a typical cell, like the neurons in our brain,
لذا، الخلية النموذجية، مثل الخلايا العصبية في دماغنا
has a region called the dendrites that receives input,
تحتوي علـي منطقة تسمى التغصنات وهي تستقبل المدخلات
and that input sums together
وهذه المدخلات تجتمع
and will produce action potentials
وتنتج جهد الفعل
that run down the axon and then activate
والتي تنزل إلى المحور العصبي وتفعّل
all the output regions of the neuron.
جميع مناطق المخرجات في الخلية العصبية.
But non-spiking neurons are actually quite complicated
ولكن الخلايا العصبية غير الشوكية معقدة إلى حد ما
because they can have input synapses and output synapses
لأن تستطيع الحصول على مدخلات وصلات عصبية ومخرجات وصلات عصبية
all interdigitated, and there's no single action potential
وجميعها تتشابك، ولا يوجد أي جهد فعل
that drives all the outputs at the same time.
والتي تدفع جميع المخرجات في نفس الوقت.
So there's a possibility that you have computational compartments
وهناك احتمالية بأن يكون لديك أجزاء حسابية
that allow the different parts of the neuron
تتيح لأجزاء مختلفة من الخلية العصبية
to do different things at the same time.
عمل أمور مختلفة في نفس الوقت.
So these basic concepts of multitasking in time
وهذه المفاهيم الأساسية للمضاعفة في الوقت
and multitasking in space,
والمضاعفة في الحيز،
I think these are things that are true in our brains as well,
وأعتقد أن هذه الأمور حقيقية في دماغنا أيضاً،
but I think the insects are the true masters of this.
ولكن أعتقد أن المتقن الحقيقي لهذا هو الحشرات.
So I hope you think of insects a little bit differently next time,
وأتمنى أن تغيروا من تفكيركم حول الحشرات مستقبلا،
and as I say up here, please think before you swat.
وكما أقول هنا، فكروا قبل أن تضربوا الذباب.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)